<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An inuectiue againste vices, taken for vertue. Gathered out of the scriptures, by the vnprofitable seruaunt of Iesus Christe, Richard Rice</title>
            <title>Invective againste vices, taken for vertue.</title>
            <author>Rice, Richard, fl. 1548-1579.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1575</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 93 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10693</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20973</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119799</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855005</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855005</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20475</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10693)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20475)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1556:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An inuectiue againste vices, taken for vertue. Gathered out of the scriptures, by the vnprofitable seruaunt of Iesus Christe, Richard Rice</title>
                  <title>Invective againste vices, taken for vertue.</title>
                  <author>Rice, Richard, fl. 1548-1579.</author>
                  <author>Crowley, Robert, 1518?-1588.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[84] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Ihon Kyngston, for Henry Kirckham,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[ca. 1575]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The preface is by Robert Crowley.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads, from recto to verso, "The destruction of small vices.".</note>
                  <note>A diatribe against playing cards, dice, tennis, bowls, etc.</note>
                  <note>Last leaf verso has printer's device, a variant of McKerrow 224.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-K⁴ L² .</note>
                  <note>Margins cropped.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Amusements --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20475:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20475:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>An inuec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue <hi>againſte vices, taken</hi> for Vertue. Gathered out of the ſcriptures, by the vnprofitable ſeruaunt of Ieſus Chriſte, <hi>Richard Rice.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Roma. xiij.</bibl> 
               <hi>¶Let vs caſte awaie the deedes of darkneſſe, and let vs put on the armour of light.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Hieronimus.</bibl> Let men firſt reade, and deſpiſe it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward, leaſt thei ſeme to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne vnknowen thynges, by no right iudgemente, but rather of a preſumpteous hatred.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Reade and iudge. But con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne not before ye reade.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶Imprinted at London by Ihon Kyngſton, for Henry Kirckham,</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:20475:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20475:2"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader, Robert Crowley wiſheth the direction of <hi>Goddes holie ſpirite.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing requeſted to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vſe this Inuectiue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte ſmall vices: I haue dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly weighed the reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s that the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor hath vſed, and doe finde that ſuche as are delited in thoſe ſmall vices, that he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueigheth againſt, maie take ſome aduau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to calumniate the aucthours doyng, for that he ſeemeth to enueigh againſte theſe ſmall vices, as againſt déedes ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden of God, that the verie deede doen, is ſynne of it ſelf, and that the doer of any of thoſe deedes, muſt néedes be acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted a ſynner, with what minde ſo euer he haue d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n it. But as the vauntage maie bée ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the vngodlie perſones, that would faine haue libertie to ſpende their whole tyme in idleneſſe and vanitie: ſo the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie mynded ſhall haue occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to flee from all vnlawfull gainenyng, &amp; to ſeke ſuche
<pb facs="tcp:20475:3"/>
recreation when neede ſhall require, as maie ſtand with the lawes of their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and tende to the glorie of GOD. I haue therefore thought it my duetie, in theſe fewe wordes, to admoniſhe the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the profit, that he maie take by the readyng hereof. Firſt, he ſhall bee put in remembraunce of that profeſſion, that he hath made in his Baptiſme, whiche is to forſake all the vanities of this wicked worlde: and that the whole courſe of a Chriſtian mannes life, ſhould bée a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall walkyng in the waie of the ſpirite, and fleyng from the waie of the fleſh. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, he ſhall bee occaſioned to ſeeke to knowe, what the woorkes of the fleſhe be, and what be the workes of the ſpirit: and to bende hymſelf rather to goe out of the waie on the righte ſide, then on the lefte, and rather to walke in the moſte rough and narrowe waie that leadeth to life, then in the broade waie that leadeth to death and deſtruction. Laſte of all, he ſhall ſee plainely painted out, the fonde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the reaſons that the fleſhly min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded men vſe, in maintainyng their leude
<pb facs="tcp:20475:3"/>
libertie, in riotous and vnlawfull game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng. The lorde Ieſus guide vs al by his holy ſpirite: ſo that the fleſhe beyng fully mortified in vs, wee maie walke in the ſpirit all the daies of this life, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ende thereof, enioye that endleſſe glorie that he hath promiſed to ſuche. <hi>AMEN.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:20475:4"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here as in the nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble woorkes of many famous men (moſte chriſten reader (many thynges in theſe oure latter age, haue been ſearched out, no leſſe neceſſarie then godlie, to the information of the congregation.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th. xxiiii.</note> That the Sainctes might haue all thynges, meete to worke withall, to the edification of the bodie of Chriſt.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eſi. iiii.</note> While many thynges haue béen neceſſarily ranſaked: other thynges very meete haue been omitted: the whiche in the ſacred woorde of God, are ſore repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended as whoredome, murther, or theft.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a. viiii</note> Not as though I, as a ſinguler perſone, would of myne owne capacitie &amp; witte, now at lengthe, take in hande to correcte <hi>Magnificat,</hi> or to pike out the Crowes eyes. But accordyng to the talente that God hath committed vnto me.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ma. xii.</note> Seyng vice ſo riſe, and dampnable before God.
<pb facs="tcp:20475:4"/>
And<note place="margin">i. Corinth. v</note> no leſſe daungerous, to the open re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porte of the conſcience of Chriſtian bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers (to whom onely, with obſcure bright<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe, I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit this little treatiſe (thought my duetie no leſſe then ſomwhat to ſaie, in the reformation of ſuche wickedneſſe.<note place="margin">ii. Timo. iiii</note> How truely and meetely, lette the woorde of God recorde. To the whiche (good Chriſtian Reader) I wholie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte thee, with the increaſe of his knowledge. Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:20475:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20475:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Lorde Ieſu Chriſte, the ſonne</hi> of the euerlaſtyng God, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorer of all puritie, giue vs grace to liue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocently in his ſight. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD the mightie ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of thynges, by his power and word (that is his welbeloued ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne and our ſauiour Chriſt Ieſu) intending for his pleaſure onelie, to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion that noble creature, and of moſte delectation in all the woorkes of his han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, ſaied as the ſcripture witneſſeth: let vs make man vnto our owne ſimilitude and likeneſſe.<note place="margin">Gene. 1.</note> In theſe twoo woordes, ſimilitude, and likeneſſe, knifyng or cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyng manne vnto hym ſelf, diſceueryng him farre bothe in knowledge and liuyng from the other woorkes of his makyng, for aſmuche as he ordained all other thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges for his commoditie and pleaſure, to obeye and ſerue hym, and that he ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:20475:6"/>
ſerue, and bee obediente to none of them all, but onely to his creatour and maker, the celeſtiall God of heauen and yearth, vnto whoſe ſimilitude, and likeneſſe he is made, in that he is made vnto his likenes it certifieth vs that he is inueſted, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with the knowledge, and vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng of Gods beneuolence toward hym, and with affections obſequious vnto rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, kindeled with the Lanterne of Gods bright countenaunce, as to knowe where as a little before, he was but a vile peece of yearth, and the dounge of the filthie grounde, that he is now made of that ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranous yearthly ſlime, a creature moſte noble and worthie, not made vnto the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keneſſe, either of the yearth, or water, either of fiſhe or foule, either of Aungell, or Archaungell, but onely vnto the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his Lorde GOD in memorie, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and pure will, the whiche he beſtowed vnto the glorie of his God that made hym, and not in vaine trifles, mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinges of folie, phantaſies of a tranſitorie and waueryng mynde, and that ſheweth well the woorde that followeth, that is,
<pb facs="tcp:20475:6"/>
that manne was made to his ſimilitude, certifiyng vs that manne, beſide that he was indewed with the Image of his lord God, with the properties before recited, yet notwithſtandyng, in as muche as ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> repreſentyng his Lorde GOD in ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, is not onely indued with theſe noble giftes: as memorie, vnderſtandyng, pure will, after the Image of his maker, but alſo with moſte excellente, and higheſte vertues after his ſimilitude, as with ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall Iuſtice, whiche is els nothyng, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng the innocencie of a pure godlie life, and a Religion of righteouſneſſe, newlie ingraffed in his harte, toward his Lorde God, and a pure obedience vnto his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes, with a ſingle eye to his neighbours profite, with the whiche pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties is he righte made vnto the ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of his Lorde God, accordyng to the ſaiyng of the holie Ghoſte in the thirde booke of Moiſes:<note place="margin">Leuiti. 11.</note> Bee ye holie, for I am holie, nowe is it manifeſte with what comely qualities, man is like his Lorde God, bothe in Image, and in ſimilitude, and thus adourned with theſe Godly or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namentes
<pb facs="tcp:20475:7"/>
and graces, he appoincted a place for hym to exerciſe theſe noble ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, and that thei ſhould not throughe ſlothfulneſſe dye in hym, as thynges of ſmall eſtimation and worthineſſe, and ſo ſente hym into Paradiſe. What to dooe there? To Bowle, or to plaie at Diſe, or Cardes, Penipricke, or ſlipthrift? Were theſe noble giftes of no higher worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, then to be beſtowed in ſuche trifles of folie? Is the memorie that his Lorde God gaue him to vſe, to the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce of his firſte makyng, no better worthe then to be exerciſed, in packyng of a carde or ſettyng of a Dye, or deliueryng of a Bowle, or inuentyng of crafte to deceiue his neighboure? For theſe or ſuche like trifles, did not God prepare Paradice for Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, with his notable giftes, and in ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, to profeſſe the truthe, it is to muche ſhame, to graunte theſe goodlie giftes to bee receiued at the handes of the moſte pure, and glorious God, and ſo wickedlie bothe againſte Goddes bleſſed pleaſure, and the vtilitie of our neighbour to bee v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, for our GOD prepared Paradice for
<pb facs="tcp:20475:7"/>
Adam to woorke in, ſaieth the texte.<note place="margin">Gene. 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> Is Bowlyng woorkyng? Is Carde plaiyng woorkyng? Is the blaſphemie of Goddes moſte holie name a woorkyng? Yea, and meete for Paradice. Is crafte, diſceiyte, guile, and diſſimulation, a woorke fitte for hym that ſhould enter into Paradice? If theſe vices and ſuche like, be not found in gamenyng, beſide chaunging of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour: ſighyng from the harte, for the loſſe of a pilde halfpenie, more then for the vaine takyng of Gods bleſſed name, with the whorlyng of the Pottes aboute the houſe, the Cardes into the fire, the Dice vnder the feete, where ſhall ye finde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? In gamening I ſaie, and not in working, and for this cauſe did God ordaine Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice for manne to worke in, indued with all theſe Godlie qualities, meete to enter into ſuche a worthie place, and there at his pleaſure to exerciſe theim to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of his Lorde GOD. But a lacke for pitie, long did no manne continue in this godlie ſtate and vocation, to occupie hym ſelf in Goddes Commaundementes, for, foorthwith did the Serpente (diſdainfull
<pb facs="tcp:20475:8"/>
of mannes felicitie) blowe ſuche blaſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> into his fleſhely eares, that he ſette a ſide his Lordes will, and gaue attendaunce, and liſtened to the voice of the Serpent, and in a momente, he loſte quite all theſe Godlie giftes, wherewith he was made vnto the Image, and ſimilitute of his Lorde God, and was redacte to ſuche pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nurie and beggerie, that he had nothyng lefte hym but ſhame onely, and had not (as the common ſaiyng is) one good poinct aboute him, and thus he ranne awaie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the preſence of his Lorde GOD, and the farther he ranne, the worſe he was, and the more ſhame followed hym, for he had neither the ſhape nor ſimilitude, that he receiued of his Lorde God to ſhewe him, as obedience, ſingleneſſe of mynde, pure abſtinence from carnall affections, origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall equitie, true religion of his celeſtiall father, ſubiection of the harte. &amp;c. But ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſimilitude of the Serpente, as ſhame, diſobedience, preſumption of ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, to be like his lorde God in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and vnderſtandyng, ready to clime vp to heauen by folly, breakyng of his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenaunte
<pb facs="tcp:20475:8"/>
with ſuche like ſhamefull, and wicked enormities, what remeadie now to reſtore this loſt Image again? Whiche is the waie to obtain this deformed ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude, to his priſtine and former ſhape a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine? Is idleneſſe the waie? Is phanſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng the waie? Is the waie by plaiyng, and ſportyng, or reſting of thy wearie bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, with the bones of a paire of Dice, or with a paire of Cardes (otherwiſe nowe called the bookes of life) and though it be ſpoken but in ieſtyng, yet is it not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for naught, for the nature of ſome is to reſte more in theim, and are more at quiete with the Ace, Kyng, Queene, or Varlet of Spades, then thei can be with a Spade to digge or delue honeſtly after Goddes preceptes for their liuyng: yea, and delighte quietlier in the Ace, Kyng, Queene, or Varlette of the Hartes, then thei dooe in the booke of life, regeſtered with the death of an vnſpotted Lambe, and ſealed with the bloud of Chriſt, ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyng from his tender harte, and thei are the moſte parte (I ſaie) verie ſorie that thei haue not wherewith to maintaine
<pb facs="tcp:20475:9"/>
ſuche an idle life continually, is this the waie now to claime the Image and ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude loſte again? No, no, whiche is then the waie? Surely Paule (moued by the ſpirit of God) findeth how to reſtore this loſte Image againe right well,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e. 4.</note> ſaiyng. So then, as concernyng the conuerſation in tyme paſte, laie from you that old man whiche is corrupte through deceiueable luſtes, and bee ye renewed in the ſpirite of your myndes, and putte on that newe man, whiche after the Image of God, is ſhapen in righteouſneſſe and true holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Here haue ye of ſaincte Paule the Image of GOD repaired againe a right. Wherin thinke ye? in deceiueable luſtes and phanſiynges of the wanton fleſhe, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Image of the olde man, corrupted by nature, no ſurely. But in righteouſnes ſaith Paule, well, is this then right that for my reſtitution and reſtauration per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in Chriſt, I ſhall now quitte and recompence the ſame, with a payre of Cardes or Dice? I would alſo learne ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie faine whether ſuch vaine paſtime be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to the olde man, or to the newe,
<pb facs="tcp:20475:9"/>
if it pertaine to the new ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then are we bound in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience continually to be plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng, carding, dicing, bowling, faring, kai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng, or ſuch like. For chriſt ſaith plainly.<note place="margin">Iohn. xiii.</note> I haue geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you to an example, that ye do as I haue doen.<note place="margin">i. Peter. ii.</note> Alſo Chriſt left vs an exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhould folow his foote ſteps, now therefore, if theſe thynges pertayne to the newe man faſhioned after Chriſt, ſhewe vnto vs clearely by the manifeſt Scriptures where wee ſhall finde them, that we may folowe chriſt in them. The text ſaieth plainely, that the newe man is faſhioned to the Image of God in holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.<note place="margin">i. Peter. ii.</note> That as hee whiche called you is holye, euen ſo be ye holye in all maner of conuerſation, all this waie, yet finde I none occaſion to followe Chriſte in ſuche trifling phantaſies. And to helpe the mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter for the.<note place="margin">Luke. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> In his Goſpell the firſt Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter ſaieth, verie godly on this wiſe, that we beyng deliuered out of the handes of our enimies, might ſerue hym without feare all the daies of our life, in ſuche ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe and righteouſneſſe as are accepts before hym: Peter ſaieth in all maner of
<pb facs="tcp:20475:10"/>
conuerſation, we muſt be holy as Chriſte is holy, but the olde man ſaieth, for a faire touche and vſe it not, wee muſte ſome time beare with the weakeneſſe of our neighbour, and if we liue in the worlde, wee muſt nowe and than dally with the worlde, the newe man ſaieth, faſhion not your ſelues like vnto this world.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m. xii.</note> And I would not aduiſe thée, for the pleaſure of this blinde world, to folowe the foliſh ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite thereof, and ſo to bee condempned with the world.<note n="*" place="margin">Cor. ii.</note> Thou wilt ſaie, I pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe not to remaine in it, but paſtime for a daie or twoo, and ſo to leaue of. Well, thou dooeſt well to laie for thy ſelfe, and to ſette Chriſte to ſcole, hee ſaieth for thy deliueraunce out of thy enimies handes, thou muſt ſerue hym in holines and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe all the daies of thy life, &amp; thou as ſum what wiſer then he, wilte keepe a daie or twoo for thyne owne paſtyme, to ſerue thy worldely affection. Nowe then belike we can not learne no ſuch daliance or vaine paſtime to pertaine to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten or newe man regenerate in Chriſte. For it is yet vnproued, and the ſcriptures
<pb facs="tcp:20475:10"/>
vnſought, and therefore on our parte vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleued: therefore ſore if ye will haue be credite them, proue it vnto vs by reaſon, and the ſacred Scriptures, and laie them plainely before vs as we haue doen, and we wil willingly receiue it with tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes, and tyll ye haue ſo doen, I praie you hold vs excuſed though wee beleue them not.</p>
            <p>Then it ſéemeth moſt lyke, that ſuche vaine triflyng paſtimes beelong to the olde man vnaquainted with Chriſte and his worde if it ſo be as it is in déede, then the text commaundeth vs to laie them a ſide, and to haue nought to do with them.<note place="margin">Col. iii.</note> Paule alſo in the ſpirite of GOD coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celleth vs to put from vs all thynges, as wrath, fearcenes, maliciouſnes, curſed ſpeaking, filthy ſpeaking out of our mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes. Nowe tell mee I praie thée, where ſhall ye finde more wrathe, diſpleaſure, hart burnyng, hate, enuie from the verie hearte, then ye ſhal doe in dicyng and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng? Yea it chaunceth oftentimes, that twoo ſhal enter into gamenyng, very good louers and fréendes, and or euer their ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mening be ended, they ſhall be mortall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies,
<pb facs="tcp:20475:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and the one readie to reuile the other ſo ſpitfully, that it is a thouſande to one if they parte without blowes. Than foloweth ſtraight waies ſuch anger that runneth into the daunger of iudgement, and Racha. That is worthy of councell, yea, and thou foole that is worthy of Hell fyre.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Ought not now gamenyng, which engendereth ſuche incommoditie, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenience, to bee auoyded as a thyng moſt daungerous, and moſt peſtilent, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them that profeſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians? Yea, ought not rather the verye Iewes and infidels, the whiche are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all godly lawes, ſauing only the lawe of their conſcience, excuſing and accuſyng them.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m. ii.</note> As their wickednes are enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to ſhunne ſuche vngodly paſtymes? yes truely ought they, then muche more thou beyng the profeſſour of Chriſtes ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Euangely, oughteſt to be an abſtayner from all thynges that haue any ſhewe or likelihoode of vice. As the good and true diſciple of Ieſu Chriſte. Sainct Peter te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Peter. ii.</note>
I beſéeche you brethren as Pyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grims and ſtraungers to abſtaine from
<pb facs="tcp:20475:11"/>
fleſhely luſtes, whiche fight againſt the ſoule: and ſée that ye haue honeſt conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation among the Gentiles, that, they whiche backebite you as euill doers, maie ſee your good workes, and prayſe God in the daie of viſitation. But thou wilt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunce ſaie, that I am to harde to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hende that thyng, that maie for an honeſt recreation bee frequented, where as the companie is ſober, and purpoſed of a gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle intent, ſecludyng blaphemie, riot, dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenſhip and ſuch like exceſſe, only for the paſſyng of tyme, to refreſhe our wittes. Wel, I heare thine excuſe verie wel, my thinke thou calleſt it an honeſt recreatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and that I am to hard to reprehende ſuch an honeſt recreation, if plaiyng at cardes or tables, ſcalyng or bowlyng, be ſuche an honeſt recreation, I pray thée for the loue of God, finde it out of the worde of God, and ſhewe it me, that I may alſo refreſhe my ſelfe, and geue thée thankes.</p>
            <p>We haue proued a little before, that they are ſuche actes as appertaine to the olde man. For we could not finde them méete for them that were faſhioned after
<pb facs="tcp:20475:12"/>
the Image of God, and ſo borne a newe, and regenerate in Chriſt, and in as much as they are the feares and béedes of the olde man, call them by what name or vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable ſo euer thou wilte, yet maie not we for the honeſt terme that thou geueſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, receiue the thing that is naught and wicked neuer the ſoner: for Paule calleth it the olde man corrupt through deceiua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble luſtes.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e. iiii.</note> And here Peter would haue vs as well acquainted with them, as a waie faryng man is in the countrie, that he neuer was acquainted or came in al his life tyme, and calleth them plainly, fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly luſtes, fightyng againſt the ſoule, hee would alſo we ſhould haue good woorkes to ſhewe among the Heathen to praiſe God with, in the daies when thou ſhalte be circumuented of the enemies of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes croſſe, and chaunceſt to be perſecuted for thy maiſters ſake, whiche hee calleth the day of viſitation, what wilt thou haue to ſhewe for thy ſelfe? ſhall any of theſe honeſt recreations, ſober paſtimes, refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyng of the witte, be taken then for good workes? bicauſe thou geueſt them honeſt
<pb facs="tcp:20475:12"/>
names, no, no, ſurely, Matthewe decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth very plainely,<note place="margin">Math. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> where he would haue our good workes for to ſhine before men, that they maie ſée our good workes, and glory our father whiche is in heauen, and ye ſhal finde that he there ſpeaketh of the ſacred Goſpell with his workes. Wil ye ſee what goodnes enſueth of your honeſt termed paſtimes? firſte where dooe chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren pitiouſly crie out for meate &amp; drinke and can not get it? forſooth, where their father is giuen to Bowlyng, Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ng, or Cardyng, Tennis plaiyng, frailyng, and ſuche like. Where doe ſeruauntes lacke worke, and ſtande whirlyng their knife aboute their fingers, and gaſing idlely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute the ſtreates and walles, to occupie the whole halfe daie in vaine language? where their maiſters be addicte to Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng, Dicyng, Tables, Cardes, Tenniſ-plaiyng, Scailyng with ſuch like. Where wanders women aboute the towne mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daie and midnight, with, wot ye where my huſband is? when ſe ye my good man? where might ſhe beſt inquire for her vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thriftie huſbande? but where the man is
<pb facs="tcp:20475:13"/>
geuen to ſuche vncomely vices?</p>
            <p>Where is the name of God wickedly blaſpemed, but in ſuche vnméete aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies? where is twelue pence ſpente be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore eight pence bee earned? but in ſuche vnlawfull gamenyng? Where flye the portes aboute the howſe? where fal men together by the eares? how come menne into extreme pouertie? when fall manne and wife to ſighyng and ſorrowyng and ſtartyng in their ſleepes, and wryngyng of their handes? but where is geuen to ſuch exceſſe in paſtime? Wher are fraies raiſed? menne ſtabbed in with woundes, and lie at their wiues handes, which hath thrée or fower children, and little woorke and ſmall frendes, and colde charitie? but where there is vſed ſuch riote and exceſſe in gamenyng. And wilt thou nowe ſaie, that a chriſten man maie exerciſe with a good conſcience that thyng that all this mhiſchefe ſpryngeth on? ſéeyng alſo they pertaine to the olde man which we ought to put from vs? and are called of Peter fleſhely luſtes alſo, the whiche we muſte abſteine from, loke now and marke if thy
<pb facs="tcp:20475:13"/>
honeſt recreation, gentle paſtime, and conuenient refreſhing of thy witte, with ſuche like comely tearmes, wyll make a wicked, a ſinfull, a deteſtable, a fleſhelie and corrupte thyng good? No, no, it will not be: therefore I hartely beſeeche thee (good chriſten reader) call me not an hard reprehender, for (before the righteous God I ſpeake it) I reprehende it none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then I haue a cauſe, and no har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der then thou thy ſelf (if thou doeſt right) oughteſt for to dooe, and I praie thee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly deſire God of his fatherly affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">i. Timo. ii.</note> in thy praier, that he will graunt to the compiler of this ſimple and rude mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.<note place="margin">Roma. i.</note> (Yet god he taketh to his conſcience faithfull and true) that he wyll kindle his harte<note place="margin">i. Peter. i.</note> With his ſacrifiyng ſpirite, that he maie leaue of (as he entendeth none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) ſuche vaine and idle trifelyng. Alſo thou ſaiſt where a ſober company is met, ſuche paſtimes may be vſed that maketh mee ſore to muſe, for I can not thinke that ſober company will take an vnſober matter in hande, yea though they were as ſober as euer was <hi>Abſtemius,</hi> as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunt
<pb facs="tcp:20475:14"/>
as euer were the <hi>Rechabites,</hi> in abſtinence.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>em. xxxii.</note> As auſtere in liuing as euer was Iohn the Baptiſer.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath. xiii.</note> As circumſpect as euer was Ioſephe in Egypte vnder Pharao.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>neſis. xli.</note> Yet if they ſhoulde goe aboute ſuche trifles of follye, and occupie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in phantaſis, inhibit by the mouth of God, I can ſee in them no ſobernes, no wiſedome, no circumſpection. But rather folly, ſoberneſſe, that is corrupt with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuable luſtes. The olde man faſhioned after the Deuill, and not after the Image of God. For what ſober companie can ye appointe me, that freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tate ſuche vaine paſtimes, the whiche after the cuſtome of the realme when they are inhibite, are called vnlawfull games? Excepte dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerdes, blaſpemers, railers, geſters, ydle talkers, that parteine nothyng to the matter.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>phe. v.</note> Be a ſober companie? excepte craftie deceiuers, ſulbtill workers, falſe diſſembles be a ſober co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panie? for marke the moſt honeſt gameſters that will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe themſelues before they enter into plaie by their falſe fidelitie, that thei will plaie neuer a Carde falſe, nor neuer an
<pb facs="tcp:20475:14"/>
Ace wrong, and when they are once en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into plaie, there ſhall be packyng of Cardes, winkyng with the eyes, blaryng out the tongue, renouncyng the Trompe and commyng in againe, and when that diſceite is ſpied, then ſhall thei fall to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonyng why he did ſo, then will thei haue an aunſwere why he hath broke his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, as though he would haue him kéepe his promiſe in a fooliſhe matter, when he breaketh his promiſe daily in a weightier and more deeper matter made betweene God and his neighbour, is not this good ſtuffe thinke you? is not this méete for a ſober companie? well go to, admitte it be méete for a ſober companie, as to take ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber men for the diſcrete men of the world (for more honeſtlier can ye not take ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernes) is it therefore (and ſpeake of pure conſcience) mete for a chriſten company? I dare boldely ſaie that the corrupt olde man ſhall neuer enter into the kingdome of heauen.<note place="margin">Coloſ. iii. Ephe. iii.</note> And if theſe bee the workes meete for a chriſten companie, then ſhall the Chriſten companie neuer come in heauen, and I marueile much alſo if theſe
<pb facs="tcp:20475:15"/>
workes be ſo meete for a chriſten compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, why Chriſt taught not his Diſciples ſuche méete workes, and the people alſo in the heauenly Sermon that he made in the Mountaine.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath. v.vi.vii.</note> Where hee bleſſed the poore in ſpirite, the mourners, the méeke, the hungrie and thirſtie for rightouſnes, the mercifull, the pure in harte, the peace makers, the ſufferers of perſecution for his names ſake, he bleſſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo which were reuiled, and ſuffered all maner euill ſaiynges for his names ſake, theſe with ſuche like were the woorkes whiche hee bleſſed. But I here not in this place that he bleſſed, either Cardes, or Dice, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to plaie at Pen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pricke with, or pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Groates to plaie at ſlipthrifte, Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis balles or bowles horſe bones for ſcai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, nor kniues for muggle pricke, nor Shaftes to darte ouer Beames in rainie daies? No, neither Dicers nor Carders, Penipricke plaiers, nor Slidethrifters, Scailers, nor Darters, Tennis plaiers nor muggle prickers, but if they had been workes méete for a chriſten companie, he would not haue forgotten them no more
<pb facs="tcp:20475:15"/>
then they did the other. But what was the occaſion that he remembred not the laſte workes in his ſermon, as well as he did the firſte? Loke and ſearche the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piters (I praie thée) and thou ſhalt mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly ſee that the former workes (which are méete in deede for a chriſten compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie) haue the promiſes of the kyngdome of heauen. But the latter workes meete for the olde man and the deuill hath not ſo, and in deede (to profeſſe the truth) thei that are well acquainted with the firſte workes, will haue no deintie in the laſte. Nowe then if the firſt workes be appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of God, méete for a chriſten aſſembly, and ſuche as haue the promiſes alſo of the kingdome of GOD, and the latter beyng fleſhely luſtes.<note place="margin">i. Peter. ii.</note> Fightyng againſt the ſoule, not ſhapen after the Image of god, but after the olde man, corrupt with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuable luſtes,<note place="margin">Coloſſ. iii.</note> deſtitute alſo of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of the celeſtiall kyngdome.<note place="margin">i. Corin. v.</note> Iudge I praie thee good reader) if thou bee not corrupt with like infection (whiche wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes bee meeteſt for a chriſten companie, as for the firſt workes we will not make
<pb facs="tcp:20475:16"/>
much mention of, for they are in caſe good enough.</p>
            <p>But let vs touche a little of the ſecond, that it maie bee to the glorie of God, and to the reformation (if it maie bée) of ſuche ſhamefull vices. What is the occaſion that the mother many tymes lacketh all the pinnes on her Pincaſe? But becauſe the parentes without the feare of GOD, bryng vp their children in wanton game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and will not rebuke them, but make theim delicate and wilfull.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. xxx.</note> What mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth that the father lacketh now and then an halfpenie, or a penie out of his pourſe? Euen for becauſe their parentes ſuffer theim to licenciouſly, to rage after their owne reane, whoſe ſonge at lengthe ſhall be full of heauineſſe. For aſmuche as thei haue rather maintained their folie in riot and gamenyng, and haue ſpared the rodde of correction, that miniſtered wiſedome, and therefore ſhall thei bee bothe father and mother broughte to ſhame.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouerb. xxix. Kinges. iii.</note> What meaneth it, that a ſober manne takyng greate care, watche, and ſtudie abroade, for his wife and childrens liuyng, cometh
<pb facs="tcp:20475:16"/>
home at night, and findeth in his houſe, in ſteede of a ſober houſwife, a thyng worſe then a Dragon, and Lyon, the Serpentes heade, chaungyng her countenaunce like a Beare, a drounken houſwife? But bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe loueth daliaunce, and paſtyme,<note place="margin">Eccle. xxv.</note> riottyng, &amp; gamenyng, one potte a beare a broade, better then twentie at home? What meaneth it that poore menne ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng muche paine for their wiues, and their own liuyng, and walke circumſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tly abroade, to fetche with their honeſte labour ſomewhat home, and at his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourne, findeth neither platter, nor diſhe charger, nor ſaucer, ſpones, nor trenchers panne, nor potte, meate, nor drinke, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thei left ſhreude houſwifes at home delightyng in riotte, and gamenyng, bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng, Cardyng, or Dicyng? What mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth that wee haue ſo many Gailes, lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and priſones, with as many yrons as thei maie bee thruſt, ſo many ſtockes and Pillories, Goſe houſes, and Cokeſtoles, Barres for thieues to holde their handes at, and Galowe trees.<note place="margin">Romanes. xi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> But becauſe the people is ſo ſore ſette on riotte.<note place="margin">Prouer. xxvi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> As the
<pb facs="tcp:20475:17"/>
games before recited, with other wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. The lord in heauen ſuppreſſe theſe vices once, that there maie bee many of theſe ſwordes, and corrections taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie. What meaneth that wee haue ſo many lane Sermones, and ſo many fatte banquettes? Becauſe there is more affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion had to the tables, then to the Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente, to the booke with twoo and fiftie leaues, then to the Bible? What is the occaſion that the woorkes of mercie are ſo ſore abated?<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath. xxv.</note> Becauſe the woorkes of the deuill, and vaine paſtyme is ſo ſore increaſed.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath. xxiiii.</note> Many mo paſtymes there bée which I am not acquainted with (though I am acquainted with to many) that ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the glorie of GOD, and depriue vs from the Image of his glorious ſonne Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte, by whom onely wee haue an enteraunce vnto the father.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n. vi.</note> Marke now good Chriſtian reader, and ponder well, whether theſe woorkes of ignoraunce, meete companions for the deuill.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me. v.</note> Theſe deceiueable luſtes.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l. iii.</note> Fleſhely affections, woorkes of dampnation, the deedes of ſynne, bee meete for an honeſt companie,
<pb facs="tcp:20475:17"/>
or not.<note place="margin">Galat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Yea, and for a Chriſtian compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, and ſpecially to bee bleſſed of Chriſt, without he bleſſe them, as he promiſed to Moiſes, with carefull curſes.<note place="margin">Leuit. xxvi. Deut. xxvi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> In the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and in the Toune, and in the fielde, in the ſtorehouſe, and in the baſkette, in the fruicte of thy bodie, that thou ſhall bée ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine, and if thou haſte any children, thei ſhall bee blinde, dombe, lame, or halte, or in the fruicte of thy lande, and curſes vpon thy Oxen, and vpon thy Shepe: In thy in going, and in thy out going, to thy deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and rebuke: to all that thou ſetteſte thy hande to, till he bryng thee to naught quickely, for the wickedneſſe of thyne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions, becauſe thou haſt forſaken thy Lorde God, and giuen thy mynde, and ſet thy hart of other trifles, with an hundred ſuche like: wee maie chaunce to haue our deedes bleſſed on this maner, and excepte we amende in tyme, after many plagues, peſtilences, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>earthes, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie, looke for none other bleſſynges and that ſhortly.</p>
            <p>God open the eyes of our Magiſtrates that thei maie ſe a redreſſe for theſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb facs="tcp:20475:18"/>
in ſeaſon, that in ſteede of ſpeakyng to a Bowle, or Die, or Carde, vnreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and dombe thinges, we maie through our praiers, and their aide, ſpeake vnto our neighbour, and our owne fleſhe, and bloudde, thynges out of the volume of the ſacred Bible, to his edification and ſoules healthe.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>t. xvii. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſuc. i.</note> As the good Diſciple of Ieſu Chriſte ſaincte Peter counſaileth vs.<note place="margin">i. Peter. iiii.</note> If any man ſpeake, lette hym talke as the woordes of God. Nowe Peter would not onely haue our deedes ſauour, and taſte of God, but alſo our ſpeache, language, and communication, would he haue ſounde as the woordes of God, or els not to ſpeake at all. Nowe then, dooe Siſe Ace, Kater Deuce, Sinke Trey, Ambes Ace, twoo Deuces, take hym nowe Dice if ye can, gentle Dice what ye will, I care not. A ſhame take theſe euill fauoured bones, a peſtilence on the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with bloud, woundes Nailes, and Harte, I would theſe Dice were burnte. Sounde theſe tearmes, I ſaie, like the woordes of GOD? Dooeth marke, well the Cardes, take heede howe he packeth them. I haue the Ace, therfore
<pb facs="tcp:20475:18"/>
muſte I robbe, with puttyng your hande to your cappe, your fiſte on a heape, your finger to your harte, kiſſyng of the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, takyng your ſelf by the noſe, with it is myne alreadie, ye plaie naughteilye, whorle, take vp, the tricke is mine, ſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully caſte: I muſte deale now, dooe theſe woordes I ſaie, ſounde as the woordes of God? Thei ſounde in deede but after the trade of the old man, and not after Chriſt after the fleſhe and her appetite, and not after the motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the ſpirite, and in that S. Peter willeth here, that our ſpeache ſhould bee as the woordes of God. Paule to the Colloſſians.<note place="margin">Col. iii.</note> Addeth to the wordes of Peter, as it were a Paraphraſes, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng it clearely out of queſtion, that all thynges what ſoeuer wée doe in woorde, or in deede, ſhould bee dooen in the name of the Lorde Ieſu, giuing thankes to God the father by hym. Looke if theſe wordes or deedes that are ſpoken of before, bee doen in the name of the Lorde Ieſu, or as Dauid in his twelue Pſalme declareth,<note place="margin">Pſalme. xii.</note> what maner of woordes, the woordes of the Lorde bee, to giue the more lighte to
<pb facs="tcp:20475:19"/>
Peters ſentence, ſaiyng: the woordes of the Lorde are pure woordes. Euen as the Siluer whiche from the yearth is tried, and purified ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tymes in the fire. Now ponder, how the wordes of the Lorde are pure woordes: and our woordes are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure, filthie, and wicked, and ſpecially in ſuche light paſtymes: pure as the Siluer tried from the yearth, are the woordes of the Lorde, and our woordes are as filthie as dounge, tried out of a filthie, and ſtyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng ſtomacſte, pollutyng, and defilyng the man.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath. xv.</note> Whereby we ſhall not miſſe, but bee condempned.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath. xii.</note> And therefore ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poincte with thy ſelf aſſuredly to giue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coumptes for all ſuche idle, vnprofitable, and vaine woordes, before the high iudge, that ſhall waigh bothe thy actes, woordes, and woorkes in a paire of euen balaunce, and rewarde thee after thy deſertes, as thou haſt wrought them in thy caranous bodie.<note place="margin">Cor. v.</note> Now yet once againe I ſaie, take heede, and bee well aduiſed what woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes ye will prepare, to appeare with be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the glorious Iudge, thou haſte nowe warnyng, and bothe the woorkes of the
<pb facs="tcp:20475:19"/>
fleſhe, and the woorkes of the ſpirite laied openly before thyne eyes, with the woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and communication, mete for a ſober, an honeſte, and a Chriſtian companie, with the contrary, and both their rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, therefore take heede and bee wiſe in tyme. Beſide this thou ſaieſt that a ſober companie, nowe and then maie exerciſe ſuche honeſte recreations, for the paſſyng awaie of the time, excludyng blaſphemie, riotte, and exceſſe. I would gladlie heare theſe recreations, whiche ye call honeſte, to bee firſte proued honeſte: before ye call theim honeſte recreations, if that bee an honeſt recreation, to exerciſe that thing, that thieues, whoremo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers, blaſphemers murtherers, dronkerdes, railers, ieſters, mockers, and ſcorners doe occupie, it is a wonders honeſt recreation. Now then I perceiue verie well, that ye can bee par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers with that wickedneſſe, that ſuche a ſhamefull rable of riottoures and dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kardes vſed, with the ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geaunce of God annexed vnto them, for where is the ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geaunce of GOD more preſente, then where the deedes of the fleſhe are exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.
<pb facs="tcp:20475:20"/>
               <note place="margin">Gala. v. Cor. v.</note> Then ye can be partakers with the poore flocke of Chriſte, that doe abhorre ſuche phantaſies, and imaginations of the Deuill,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>n. viii.</note> wholie addicte to an honeſte pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of liuyng, and to the ſearchyng of the ſacred will of God, out of the holie Bible, Chriſt beyng in the middes of them.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> xvi.</note> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſte recreations are meete for honeſte menne, but Cardyng, Dicyng, Bowlyng, Scailyng, and Tennis plaiyng, are not honeſt recreatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: <hi>Ergo</hi> thei are not méete for honeſte menne. If thei bee honeſte re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creations, then thefte is an honeſt recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then is murther an honeſte recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then is whoredom an honeſt recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for thynges worthie like praiſe, are of like honeſtie, and worthy like reward: But thefte, murther, whoredome, with other like deedes of the fleſhe, are worthy like praiſe. <hi>Ergo</hi> like honeſt, and worthie like reward. For what praiſe is a wicked thyng worthie, but the curſſe of God and dampnation? As the Scribe in the nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tene of Matthewe,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. xix.</note> demaunded of Chriſte what he might doe to haue eternall life? Chriſte aunſwered, thou ſhalt not ſteale:
<pb facs="tcp:20475:20"/>
Thou ſhalte not breake wedlocke: Thou ſhalte not kill. Now if the Scribe, or any other Chriſtian man, will haue eternall life, he muſt obſerue theſe preceptes, that he be no thiefe, no whoremonger, nor no murtherer. If he bee, then lette hym not looke for eternall life: for he that keepeth the commaundementes, dwelleth in God and God in hym.<note place="margin">i. Iohn. iiii.</note> Then let vs thus rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, he that keepeth not the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, dwelleth not in God. But he that is a theife, whoremonger, or murtherer, kepeth not the commaundementes. <hi>Ergo</hi> he is a thiefe, whoremonger, or murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, dwelleth not in GOD: and he that dwelleth not in God, hath no life in hym.<note place="margin">Iohn. i.</note> In him is life, and the life was the light of menne. &amp;c. Alſo Dauid ſaieth plainely.<note place="margin">Pſalme. i.</note> The wicked ſhall not riſe in iudgement becauſe thei are alwaie deade (ſaieth <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi>) from GOD, and ſhall not riſe to life; and he that hath not life in God, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie addicte to dampnation. Example of Cain the firſte murtherer,<note place="margin">Gene. iiii.</note> whiche ran awaie from the preſence of God, in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is life: and the whoredome of the people
<pb facs="tcp:20475:21"/>
of Iſraell, with the doughters of Moab. <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um. xxv.</note> Nume. xxv. Reade the whole Chapiter, I praie thee. Iudas the thiefe and purſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearer.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>hn vi. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath. xxvi.</note> Now the thiefe, the whoremon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and murtherer haue no life in God, therefore the thiefe, whoremonger, and murtherer, are addicte to dampnation, then if the deedes of the fleſhe (for better deedes can ye not make them, for thei wil in no wiſe agree with the deedes of the ſpirite) bee worthie like rewarde and dampnation: then it followeth, that they are like euill and wicked vices, like abhominable in the ſight of GOD, are worthie like dampnation: but Bowlyng, Dicyng, Cardyng, Tenneſyng, with ſuch like actes and deedes of the fleſhe, are of like rewarde and dampnation, with mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whoredome, and theft. <hi>Ergo</hi> thei are like abhominable and wicked, that thei are of like da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation is manifeſt.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om. viii.</note> Where with a godly antitheſis or contrarietie he pronounceth it on this ſorte, there is no dampnation to them, which are in Chriſt Ieſu, whiche walke not after the fleſhe, but after the ſpirite. Now ſaieth Paule,
<pb facs="tcp:20475:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to be in Chriſt Ieſu is no damnation, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they walke in a newe Godly life, after the ſpirite faſhioned, and not after the fleſhe, then if there be no damnation to them that are in Chriſte Ieſu, bicauſe they walke after the ſpirite, it foloweth on the other partie, that there is damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to them that are not in Chriſt Ieſu, bicauſe they walke after the fleſhe. But Dicers, Bowlers, Carders, Scailers, Croſſers and Pilers, Teneſſers, Cheſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers with ſuch like a thouſand mo, when they are in their moſt honeſteſt paſtime, ſecluding (as thei ſay) blaſphemyng, riot, and exceſſe, yet are they in the deedes of the fleſhe. Therefore is there alſo ſuche damnation after the ſentence of Saincte Paule, For bee not a ſhamed hardely to nomber theſe honeſt recreations amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt deedes of the fleſhe, till ye can by the Scripture diſcharge them thereof. Loke alſo,<note place="margin">Math. vii.</note> where he maketh a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene the good Trée and her fruite, and the bad tree and her fuicte: and ſaie of an honeſt hearte, in whiche of theſe Trees, bowlyng cardyng, with the reſidue of
<pb facs="tcp:20475:22"/>
their fruites, growe. And he ſaieth in the ſame place, that euerie Tree that bryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth not foorth good fruite, ſhall be caſte into the fyre.<note place="margin">Gala. v.</note> And Paul to the Gallathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, verie plainly declareth the ſentence of Matthewe, and nameth both the trees with their fruites, and calleth the good tree, the ſpirite, and the deedes thereof, the fruites of the ſpirite. But in thoſe fruites ſhall ye finde no place for none of theſe dedes, the words are theſe: the frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the ſpirite, loue, Ioye, long ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce, gentlenes, faithfulnes, mekenes, goodnes, temperaunce. Now marke wel this good trée, and ſhewe me what fruite or braunche thereof ye can finde meete, for to place your honeſt paſtimes, good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhyng of the witte, the paſſyng awaie of the tyme, and with riot and ſuche lyke vaine trifles. The fruites of the euill tree are theſe: aduoutrie, fornication, vnclea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, wantonnes, Idolatrie, witchcrafte, hatred, variaunce, wrath, ſtrife, ſedicion, ſectes, enuie, murther, dronkennes, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonie, couetouſnes, pride, lecherie, bacbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng, diſcorde, and innumerable ſuche
<pb facs="tcp:20475:22"/>
like. If you marke theſe fruictes wel, you maie chaunce to finde ſome braunches, meete for your purpoſe. How be it, if any manne bee ſo addicte to follie, that though he ſeeth it, he will not ſee it, leaſte his ſynne ſhould be reproued, I ſhall take the paines my ſelf (though I haue little tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke therefore) to ſette one or twaine before your eyes, and if you haue any felicitie or pleaſure, in the ſearchyng out of the holie worde of God, you ſhall verie eaſily with your ſtudious indeuour, finde out the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidue right well. Firſte, what ſaie you to this braunche of vncleaneſſe, maie it not take place (thinke you) emong your vaine paſtyme? I ſuppoſe the deedes of the fleſh bee not cleanly, but your recreations are before proued to be dedes of the fleſh. <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go</hi> your fooliſhe vaine recreatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, are not verie cleanly, therefore laie vp this fruict of vncleaneſſe, to bee one of your preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous iewelles to ſerue you a purpoſe. How like ye alſo by wantonneſſe, maie ye not bee nombred well inoughe emong youre vaine ſporte and paſtyme?<note place="margin">i. Peter. iiii.</note> Looke the firſt and fowerth Chapiter, where he decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
<pb facs="tcp:20475:23"/>
how we ſhould arme our ſelfes with the ſame mynde, to ceaſe from ſynne, by ſufferyng in the fleſhe, as Chriſte did, and to liue after the will of GOD. He addeth ſtraight waies, that it is ſufficient for vs, that we haue ſpent the tyme that is paſt, of the life, after the will of the Heathen, and Gentiles, walkyng in wantonneſſe, fleſhely luſtes, in exceſſe of wines, in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of eating, in dronkenneſſe, and in ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable Idolatrie. Here Peter rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth wantonneſſe, to pertaine to the life of the wicked Gentiles.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er. ii.</note> To luſtes, Peter before in the ſeconde Chapiter ſaith, that thei fighte againſte the ſoule: and here he ſaieth plainely, that thei induce vs vnto abhominable Idolatrie. For what can bée greater Idolatrie, then to departe from the Lorde GOD, through inticyng of the fleſhe, and wantonneſſe, to cleaue to the wicked Gentiles, whiche are ſtraungers from the life that is in GOD, blinded in their vnderſtandyng, and walkyng in the vanitie of their fooliſhe myndes?<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e. iiii.</note> Now good Chriſtian Reader, accordyng to the affection that thou haſte to Goddes moſte
<pb facs="tcp:20475:23"/>
bleſſed woorde, ſearche out the reſidue. Nowe maie you expreſſely perceiue and ſee,<note place="margin">Math. vii<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> bothe what Matthewe in the ſeuenth chapiter, meaneth by the good tree, which Paule calleth the ſpirite, and her fruictes, doeth Paule call the deedes of the ſpirite. Where he excludeth the fleſhe, with all her appetites, luſtes, and concupiſcences. And that, that Matthewe calleth the euil tree, Paule calleth the fleſhe: and by the fruictes thereof, the deedes of the fleſhe. In the whiche is conteined, all your fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paſtymes, honeſt recreations, ſober re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhyng of the wit, with ſuche like. And where Matthewe ſaieth, that euery euill tree ſhall bee cutte doune, and caſte into the fire: Paule ſaieth manifeſtly, that as many as commit ſuche thynges, ſhall not inherite the kyngdome of God. And to be excluded out of the kyngdome of GOD, and to be hewen doune, and caſte into the fire: Is to taiſte dampnation. For howe farre was that braunche from dampnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that was cutte from the tree, and caſt into the fire? After his fine Reines and Purple, and delicious fare, doeth not the
<pb facs="tcp:20475:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
texte ſaie, that he deſcended into hell, and was ſore torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted in the flambe.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ke. xvii. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Paule alſo to the Epheſians ſaieth, that neither filthineſſe, neither fooliſhe talkyng, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ieſtyng, whiche are not comely, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any vncleane perſone, hath any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritaunce in the kyngdome of Chriſte, and of GOD. And how farre is it (thinke ye) from dampnation to bee ſeparate, and deuided from the kyngdome of Chriſte and God. Is there any Saluation, but in Chriſte onely?<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctes. iiii.</note> Luke ſaieth plainly naye. There is none other name giuen vnto vs wherin we muſt be ſaued: And therefore ſaieth Matthewe in his firſte Chapiter,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath. .i</note> that he ſhall ſaue the people from their ſynne. Then is there no Saluation ſaue onely in Chriſte, then without Chriſte is there nothyng but dampnation. And is there any life but in GOD onely? Sainct Ihon ſaieth naie in his firſte Chapiter of his Goſpell.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>hn. i.</note> Nowe, for as muche as there is no ſaluation but in Chriſte onely, and no life but in God: and ſeyng alſo, that to haue no ſaluation, nor life in god, is plain dampnation, then the deedes of the fleſhe
<pb facs="tcp:20475:24"/>
as youre fore ſaied paſtymes, are plaine dampnation, becauſe thei haue no ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Chriſte, nor life in God, nor any inheritaunce in the kyngdome of God and Chriſte. Now ſee you plainely, that theſe filthie deedes of the fleſhe (as the games before named, when thei are moſte pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vſed) are of like dampnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, with mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and thefte: <hi>Ergo</hi> thei are like wicked and abhominable. At this tyme ſatiſfie your ſelues (I praie you) with theſe ſmal warnynges, gentle admonitions, and daungerous threatenynges: and if ye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde not this, then ſuppoſe not the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie, but that there ſhall bee a more weightier matter laied to your charge, and the ſpirit of Goddes mouthe ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroye bothe you and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> together. There<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore awake betyme, and putte from you the woorkes of darkeneſſe, that you maie walke honeſtly while it is daie.<note place="margin">Roma. xiii.</note> Now at the laſte you ſaie, for the paſſing awaie of the tyme: wee maie exerciſe ſuche vaine paſtymes and recreations, and that I wil goe aboute to withdrawe honeſte menne from their honeſte fellowſhippes, famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>are
<pb facs="tcp:20475:25"/>
neighbourhoode, neighbourly metin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and aſſemblies. And will alſo (I am ſure) demaunde of me, what I would ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſte companie ſhould doe? How I would thei ſhould bee occupied, and paſſe awaie the tyme, the howers, the daies, and the nightes? If all theſe before named paſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, and recreations were laied a ſide, I ſhall ſhortely ſaciate this queſtion, euen with the ſaiyng of Salomon in his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbes,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ouerb. xxvi.</note> who ſaith thus. Giue not the foole an aunſwere after his fooliſheneſſe, leaſt thou become like vnto hym. But make the foole an aunſwere, accordyng to his fooliſhneſſe, leaſt he bée wiſe in his owne conceipte. Here maie you perceiue (if you liſte) that I compte not this queſtion ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie wiſe. For the fleſhely children of this wicked worlde, thinke this a right nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble queſtion. Yea, and worthie to bee ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted or aunſwered, with greate witte, diſcretion and learnyng, when in verie deede it is nothing els, but vnlearned and witleſſe, and therefore, accordyng to the Prouerbes of Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not worthie to be aunſwered, leaſte the fooliſhe reioyce in
<pb facs="tcp:20475:25"/>
his folie. For if this queſtion, or ſuche like were worthie aunſwere, and that a man were bounde to ſatiſfie them, I dare bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaie, that there ſhould bee more queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, then might well either with reaſon, or learnyng bée aunſwered. For this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is a greate deale meeter for Ethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nickes, Turckes, Iewes, and Saraſins, then it is for ſober menne, then it is for diſcrete menne, then it is for Chriſtian men, or for godlie diſpoſed perſones. For will not the banketters (thinke ye) after their gurgitation, and rauenous deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng of their deintie meates, and ſweete wines, demaunde with idle braines and beallies, what ſhall wée dooe all this daie? How ſhall we bryng this longe daie at an ende? How ſhall we ſpende our tyme? Is not there (thinke you) good, honeſte, and verteous bargaines made, with, we twoo againſt you twoo, for what wager ſo euer ye will, either at Tables, Dice, Cardes, Tennis, or Bowles, as longe as a Riall, twentie ſhillynges, or fowertie ſhillyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges will laſte, or till wee goe to Supper? And to make vp the bargaine, thei laſhe
<pb facs="tcp:20475:26"/>
out one othe vpon an other, in ſuche wiſe, that there ſhall bee neuer a member of Chriſt, vnſought, or torne, ſo that it maie come to memorie. Yea, the honeſteſt ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in a toune, if he beginne once to face, will thinke ſcorne to bee outſworne for four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſhillynges at Bowles, Cardes, Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, or Dice. Will not drounkardes alſo muſe with them ſelues, where thei maie gette a companie meete for their diete, to paſſe awaie the tyme, in gloſſyng and gul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng, either at ſuche tyme as it wer more méete for them to pleaſe their Lorde god. If thei be of the Spirituall ſorte, with la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouryng in the ſacred woorde of God, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eede their flocke on the Sabboth, or holy daie nexte inſuyng: Or if thei bee of the laye ſorte, to bee occupied in his miſterie, or occupation for his houſholde or fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie: or els at ſuche tyme, as it were meete for ſober, diſcrete, and honeſte menne to be at their reſt: For the which thing, God made the night? What dooe poore labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng menne, that haue twoo or three chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and nothyng but their manuall, and handie craft, to ſuccour them ſelues, their
<pb facs="tcp:20475:26"/>
wife and familie. Will not thei (thinke you) alſo ſtudie to riotte aboute ſtreates, and lanes, ſearching out a companie mete for them, in Ale houſes, and béere houſes, and inuente how their may bryng the day at an ende, and occupie their tyme in riot and gamenyng, their wiues and children in the meane while at home, criyng out for victualles, and can gette none, for the good manne of the houſe, hath beſtowed al his money ſo warely at Sice and Cinck or haue at all: or at the Spades, Hartes, Diamondes, and Clubbes, and commeth home at nighte, with as many faces as a Shéepe, &amp; can ſpeake neuer a good worde, neither to wife nor childe, and yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtandyng, muſte it bee called an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſte paſtime, and ſober refreſhyng of the witte. And thus dooe thei paſſe awaie the tyme, the howers, the daies, and the nigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. And why is this vice ſo ſlowely defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced? Becauſe that in the myndes of the Starres, the Moone ſhineth verie darck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and thei are bothe giltie of one offence, ſo that if the heades would redreſſe theſe vices, the members would aunſwere. O
<pb facs="tcp:20475:27"/>
Hypocrite, caſte out the beame that is in thyne eye firſte, that thou maieſt perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee, to pull out the moate, that is in thy brothers eye.<note place="margin">Luke. vi.</note> For what doe we, but that wee ſee it firſte ſpryng from you? Well, you wote what I meane, amende it ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in time, leaſt you chaunce to gette an afterclappe, I meane the ſworde, Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, or dearth ſente from GOD, for the correction of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Will not the whoremonger alſo muſe with hym ſelfe, how he maie beſtowe the tyme, to obteine his fleſhelie and filthie purpoſe of an harlot? Will not the thiefe likewiſe, and Scailers and Eueſdroppers of mens houſes, perpend and waie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in themſelues, where they maie beſtowe the tyme to obteine their preie, put man, woman and child, in ſore feare and dread, and many tymes in ieopardie of their ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues? And now at the laſt commeth forth theſe ſober men, with their honeſt felow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, ſometyme from their couches be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they haue giuen GOD thankes for their reſt, and as ſoone as they haue ſaied good morrowe to their neighbour, do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde
<pb facs="tcp:20475:27"/>
of hym what they maie dooe, to paſſe awaie the tyme, till they goe to din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. And ſome, to make the matter ſure, ſmite vp the bargaine ouer night, to bee in a readineſſe againſt the next morning. Some at their vnthankefull breakefaſt or dinner, ſhall couenaunt, to prayſe God all the daye vnto night for his aboundant benefites, with blaphemies, periuries, and abhominable othes, in their honeſt paſtimes? Call you this your neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie meetynges, aſſembles, honeſt neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhoode and familiare fellowſhippe to paſſe awaie the tyme? Conſider (I praie you) what a wicked rable ye haue anne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xed vnto you. For in that demaunde wyll théeues, whoremongers, murtherers, dronkardes, railers, ſcoffers, vilanes, ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, Ieſters and ſcorners bee partakers with you. And thinke you that this is not a bleſſed company, to be matched withal, in theſe ſhamefull and deteſtable vices of the fleſhe. Might not a man (if nede were) aſke you alſo this queſtion, whether all thinges be ſo ſurely ſtaied, ſo circumſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ordered, ſo warely prouided for, and in
<pb facs="tcp:20475:28"/>
ſuche pure ſtate, that there maie ſo great leaſure bee had to ſuche vanities of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtime, to the daungerous loſſe of tyme, ſo precious a Iewell? Is all (thinke you) ſo rightly handeled, both towards god &amp; our neighbour, that eche of theſe thynges ſet a part, ye maie fréely apply your mindes, to dalliyng with wanton ſportes and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menyng? Is the true worſhip of God ſo mainteined in all places, that there lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth nothyng to bee redreſſed therein.<note place="margin">Iohn. iiii.</note> And will you yet aſke mée, how ye ſhould bee occupied and paſſe the tyme awaie, if ſuche vanities were laied aſide? Is the worde of the moſt high God, purely, ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely and truelie preached in all Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ke. xix.</note> and euery Churche rid of a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſte, and a true preacher in his roome? Is true praier, that ſhould incenſe vs, with ardent affection to our heauenly fathers will, allowed for his anointed Chriſtes ſake, exerciſed aright in all places? Is blaſphemie ſo well abated,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>d. xx.</note> that there nedeth no reformation for it? Is hipocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie and the ſtraunge worſhippyng of the true God, with the obſcuryng of daies, ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes
<pb facs="tcp:20475:28"/>
and monethes.<note place="margin">Gala. iiii.</note> And the holdyng in of the people,<note place="margin">Eſaie. i.</note> with ſuch trifles as he can not abyde, cleane taken awaie from the chriſten congregation? Are Burroughes, Villages, Townes, Corporations and Cities, indued with ſober, graue and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent officers and councellers,<note place="margin">Exodus. viii.</note> abhorring auarice, coueteouſnes, ſeking the publike and common commoditie, handlyng the lawe in the true feare of god, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte of perſons.<note place="margin">Leuiticus. xix</note> Are lawes ſo indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently vſed, withouth fauouryng of the poore, and honouryng of the mightie in righteous iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,<note place="margin">Leuiticus. xi.</note> without rewards, giftes and bribes, that no man hath cauſe to complaine? Is the pouertie ſo honeſtly prouided for, both in meate, drynke and cloth, and houſes founded for the ſicke, ſore, blind, domme and lame, with honeſt pencions parteining to the ſame, and the deacons appointed for the purpoſe, beyng men notable in word and wiſedome, and of honeſt report, and ful of the holy ghoſt: meete for ſuch a nedefull buſines and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie office.<note place="margin">Actes. vi.</note> Doe the Curates ſo ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly fauour the flocke of the lorde, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:20475:29"/>
hauocke makyng of the ſame: prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching to them the pure and ſincere trueth and veritie, without fainyng Fables, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les or lyes:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ro. xxxiii.</note> Conuertyng the hearers, both with woordes and life, ſeekyng the health of his poore afflicted, comfortyng them that be in heauines and care, byn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng vp the wounded heartes, preaching deliueraunce to them that be captiue, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claryng the acceptable yere of the Lorde and the feareful daie of vengeau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of our God<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ic. xli.</note>? Are there ſuche honeſt and godlie ſcholes, and places of vertuous and godly exerciſe, in corporations, borrowes tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and faire Cities,<note place="margin">Regum. 16.</note> for the bryngyng vp and honeſt nurteryng of children, and their tutours and ſcholemaiſters,<note place="margin">Regum. 2.</note> tryed by men of grauetie and pure literature, in what kynde of doctrine they exerciſe them, either, with ſuche learnyng as ſhal afterwarde make for the glory of our hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenly father, and the edification of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of Chriſtes flocke, or in ſuche wicked doctrine, as ſhall pertaine to the ſubuerſion both of themſelues and of the communaltie, (for in them is the expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,
<pb facs="tcp:20475:29"/>
as well of vertue as of vice in all realmes) and is the due inquiſition of the ſame made in all quarters? Is there alſo diligente ſearche in all places, for falſe waightes and meaſures: that menne in buiyng and ſellyng, ſuſteine neither da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage nor loſſe.<note place="margin">Prouerb. xvi.</note> Is there ſuche loue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt neighbours, that euery manne would no worſe to his neighbour, then to his owne hearte.<note place="margin">Math. vii.</note> And if it do happen or chaunce that any perſone breake loue, ſo that ſtrife, variaunce, diſcorde, debate and hatred do riſe and growe betwene neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and neighbour, are the curates (for the which thyng they receiued that ſame appellation) or the eyes of the pariſhe (o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe called, in our phraſe of ſpeache, the heades of the pariſhe) readie (as their duetie is) to reconciliate and to bring this putrified wound to a concorde.<note place="margin">Math. v.</note> If theſe thinges, with many other, be in ſuch caſe that in none of them there needeth refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation: there maie the more libertie bee geuen, to your honeſt recreatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ſober paſtimes. But if they be not dooen, take heede, how ye meddle with the other ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt
<pb facs="tcp:20475:30"/>
recreations and paſtimes. For re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that ye are thei that muſt beare the greate charge and burden of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.<note place="margin">Deut. i.</note> Vnto whom, for conſcience ſake, the people muſt be in ſubiection.<note place="margin">Roma. xiii.</note> Foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche as ye haue the ouerſight of them, and ought ſo dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to ſtudie and waite for them, as if you ſhould giue accoumpte (as you ſhall in deede) for the ſoules of the ſubiectes. Therfore beware, that ye may make that greate accoumpte, with ioye and not with griefe.<note place="margin">Hebre. xiii.</note> Now, therefore do I ſore muſe, how this queſtion (except it were by the priuy ſuggeſtion of Sathan,<note place="margin">Sene. iii.</note> worker of all miſchiefe) coulde ſinke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any honeſt, &amp; ſpecially, into any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian mans ſtomake, to demaunde, what they ſhoulde doe, or howe they ſhoulde be occupied, if theſe ſinfull paſtymes (other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe called honeſte recreations) were laied aſide? If you woulde be as diligent to demaunde howe ye ſhoulde liue well, howe ye ſhoulde behaue youre ſelues to pleaſe GOD, howe ye might remaine in the feare and dreade of God, as ye are to inquire for ſuche vaine trifles: oh lorde
<pb facs="tcp:20475:30"/>
what a worlde ſhould we then haue ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tly? And in conſcience, I ſuppoſe, that this is the more meeter queſtion of bothe, for a Chriſtian man to demaunde. For with what face, dareſte thou enterpriſe, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire how thou ſhalte conſume the daie, in ſuche wicked paſtymes: with the abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations that longeth there to (as the blaſphemie of Goddes moſte holy name, dronkenneſſe, exceſſe, with many other more ſuche like) ſeyng and conſideryng, that thou art not certain, nor ſure to liue the halfe daie? Dooeſt thou thinke it no daunger, to fall into the handes of the Lorde,<note place="margin">Hebrewes. x.</note> Haſte thou no more dread of him that is able to kille bothe thy bodie and ſoule, and to caſte theim bothe into helle fire?<note place="margin">Math. x.</note> Now ponder (I praie thee) the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scriptures that followe, what occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation and buſineſſe, ye ſhould by their counſaile haue, if theſe fooliſhe paſtymes were ſet a parte.<note place="margin">Math. xxiiii.</note> Matthewe ſaith, wake becauſe you knowe not what hower your maiſter will come. Of this be you ſure, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if the houſholder knewe, what houre the thefe would come, he would ſurely watch
<pb facs="tcp:20475:31"/>
and not ſuffer his houſe to bee broken vp. Therefore bee ye alſo readie. For, in an hower as you thinke not, will the ſoonne of manne come. Heare ye this ye ſluggar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des? Matthewe biddeth you wake: ye wil ſaie. We are neuer leſſe diſpoſed to ſlepe, then when wee are at Tables, Cardes, Dice, Bowles, Tennes, or Cheſſe. I graunt that to be very true. But wil that buſineſſe pleaſe youre heauenly maiſter, when he commeth ſodainely vppon you? Matthewe would haue you as diligente to prepare, againſte the commyng of the Lorde: to vanquiſhe and driue awaie, the aſſaultes of the Deuill, as the houſholder is diligente to prepare weapons againſte the commyng of the Theefe, that would breake vp his houſe, And would the houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder (thinke you) fall to Cardes, Dice, Tennes, or Bowles, if he knewe when the theefe would come vpon hym? Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thewe ſaieth plainely naye, but he would watche ſaieth he, if he knewe what ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer the theefe would come, and prepare weapons to keepe hym of. And wilt thou (ſeeyng thou arte vncertaine, when the
<pb facs="tcp:20475:31"/>
Lorde will come, as the houſholder is, what hower the theefe will come) applie thy ſelf to Dice, Tables, and Cardes, and ſuffer the houſe of the liuyng God to bee broken vp? For the temple of God is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (ſaieth ſaincte Paule) whiche are ye, <note place="margin">i. Cor. iii.</note> and thinke ye that there oughte not as greate ſtudie to bee taken, for to defende the houſe that God made to his owne ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude and likeneſſe.<note place="margin">Gene. 1.</note> And redeemed with his precious death.<note place="margin">i. Peter. i.</note> From the ſna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of the wicked, againſte the commyng of his maiſter: as there oughte to bee for an houſe, that is made of lime and ſtone, and is in ſubiection to euery tempeſte of water and winde? The whiche alſo was builded of a ſynfull manne, and paied for, with corruptible ſiluer and golde, that at his diyng daie, ſhall bidde his Maiſter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dewe, and neuer doe hym pleaſure after? The inſtrumentes that ye muſt prepare, to keepe awaie the theefe, againſte youre Maiſters commyng, are not Boules, dice Cardes, Tables, Bowes, Kniues, Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, Balles, Cheſſemen, Counters, pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Grotes, Toppes and Scourges, with
<pb facs="tcp:20475:32"/>
ſuche like a thouſande mo: whiche the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill hath inuented,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ke. xiii.</note> no, no. Sainct Luke in his thirtene Chapiter, telleth vs of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther maner of inſtrumentes, to paſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie the tyme with, then theſe bee, he ſaieth with a deepe ſtomacke, take héede, watche and praie, for ye knowe not whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the tyme is, and that I ſaie to you, I ſaie to you all, watche. Luke would haue a Chriſtian mannes inſtrumente to occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie hymſelf withall, and to paſſe awaie the tyme, to conſiſt in watchyng and prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng, and the fleſhly children of this world would haue it to conſiſte in Dicing, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng, Boulyng, and Tennes plaiyng, thou wilte ſaie that it will irke, and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie one, euer to be watchyng and praiyng. I ſaie vnto thee, that of the aboundaunce of the harte, the mouthe ſpeaketh, for a good manne, out of the good treaſure of his harte, bryngeth for the good thynges.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th. xii.</note> As to doe all thyng what ſoeuer thei go aboute, either in woorde or deede, in the name of the Lorde Ieſu, giuyng thankes to God the father, by hym: And to applie them ſelues, to watchyng, praiyng, and
<pb facs="tcp:20475:32"/>
readyng of the ſacred ſcripture: as the fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes that ſpring out of the good treaſure of their hartes. But an euill manne, out of the euill treaſure of his harte, bryngeth for the euill thynges, as Dicyng, Carding with ſuche more a greate noumber. For, if he had any better treaſure, liyng in his hearte, he would ſurely bryng it foorthe. But he hath no better, that he can take a manne of truſte, therefore euill as thei bee, ſo he vttereth them: For as thei lye Canckerfretted at his hearte, ſo he laieth theim foorthe, take theim vp who liſte: therefore of thyne owne mouthe I iudge thee. Thou euill ſeruaunte,<note place="margin">Luke. xix.</note> canſte thou finde in thy harte, to paſſe awaie the time with Cardes, Tennis, Tables and Dice daie and nighte, without wearineſſe and care? And ſaieſt thou, to watche and pray and to be giuen to the wholſome medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Goddes woorde, will wearie any manne? Seyng the firſte is abrode pathe, leadyng to deſtruction, the whiche theſe vnthriftie gameſters, can finde out readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enough. The laſte is a verie narrowe pathe, leadyng to life and ſaluation,<note place="margin">Math. vii.</note> the
<pb facs="tcp:20475:33"/>
whiche is not yet troden out of theim: for it is vnſearched for.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ke. xxii.</note> Luke in the twelue Chapiter alſo ſaieth, Lette your loynes bee girte rounde aboute, and your lightes burnyng, and your ſelues ready like men, that waite for their maiſter, when he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth from the weddyng, that as ſone as he commeth, and knocketh, thei maie ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto hym. Bleſſed are thoſe ſeruauntes, whiche the lorde when he commeth, ſhall finde wakyng. Here I thinke Chriſte bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roweth a ſimilitude of theim, that in the night tyme, vſe to prepare them ſelues in a readineſſe, againſt their maiſters com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng home from the weddyng, becauſe he would haue them ſo handſomely girte, that thei maie walke with the leſſe lette and impedimente. But I thinke, if wee ſhould walke in the nighte, after our ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſte paſſyng awaie of the tyme, to mete with our maiſter, we had néede I ſuppoſe to be well couered about our heades, leaſt the winde make our braines diſſie, and we ſtagger out of the righte pathe, and reele like nighte riottours, and dronkar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and thei that walke in the night. For
<pb facs="tcp:20475:33"/>
the moſte parte vſe to carrie lighte with theim (ſpecially if thei fetche home any greate manne) for in the broade daie, thei vſe to carrie no lightes (as the ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſorte haue vſed now of late daies: and as ſome yet at this preſente dooe, if thei were well ſought out) for no better will their Curates teache them: but to lighte Candelles in the cleareſt Sonne ſhine in the yere, and ſticke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon poſtes, ſtoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, and walles, before Idolles, to ſhewe them light, and yet thei them ſelues with their Idols remaine ſtarke blinde. What thinke ye that theſe lightes hee, that ye muſte meete hym with, cardes, tables, or Dice, and other ſuche like tromperies? Surelie thei ſhall ſhewe a faire lighte. And as well ſhall hee welcome you with them, as he did the fiue fooliſhe virgines, which had no oyle of their owne, but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt came, they were faine to go a bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowyng, and when they came and knoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, were ſhut out of the doores.<note place="margin">Math. xxv.</note> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware ye paſſe not awaie the tyme ſo long with ſuche vaine follye, that youre good workes bee to ſéeke, and then ye knocke
<pb facs="tcp:20475:34"/>
tarde at Heauen Gates, and for lacke of knowledge, ye be ſhut out of the doores. Take heede in tyme, for thoſe ſeruauntes ſhalbe bleſſed, whom the Lorde when he commeth, ſhall finde wakyng.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ke. xii. Theſ. v.</note> ſaieth, that the daie of the Lorde, ſhall come as a thiefe in the night, for when they ſhall ſay, peace and no daunger, then commeth there on them ſodaine deſtruction, as the trauailyng of a woman with childe: and they ſhall not eſcape. Heare ye this ye blaſphemers? Heare ye this thyng, ye wicked gameſters? Heare ye this thyng, ye wittie &amp; fleſhly children of this world? Nowe go to, applie your buſines, to the Cardes, Tables, Dice, Tennes, Cheſſe and Bowles, as faſte as ye can: for the Lorde will come at your pleaſure, when ye will, and not before ye will haue hym come. So will the thiefe come and reaue vp your houſe, and not before. Plie youre buſines, as faſte as ye can: haſte vp your wickedneſſe, and lette not for it: neither care for any threatnyngs at gods mouth, for he is to weake to perfourme his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe. But of this be ye ſure, that as iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:20475:34"/>
as a teming woman that is with child, muſt needes ſuffer the trauaile thereof, whether ſhe will or no, and can not auoid it. Euen ſo, thinke not the contrarie, but when the Lorde commeth, ye ſhalbe ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken as he findeth you, and ſhal not eſcape, but as ye haue wrought the woorkes of your bodie, ſo muſt ye (ſpite of youre gut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes) appeare before the iudgement ſeate of Chriſte, to giue your accomptes.<note place="margin">i. Cor. v.</note> Be pacient and ſettle youre heartes, for the commyng of the lorde draweth nigh. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde the iudge ſtandeth before the doore, Iaco. v Here Iames plaieth the bug with you, and in a maner, mouth to mouth:<note place="margin">Iames. v.</note> he maketh hym to knock at the doore of your conſcience, that ye ſhoulde in tyme, if it might bee, withdrawe your ſelues from ſuche vanitie. Is it meete thinke you to paſſe awaie the tyme with ſuche trifles, when the iudge ſtandeth at the doore? but if ye will needes vpon ſuch foliſhnes not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding al theſe comminations and threatninges, beware I ſaie, for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng of the Lorde draweth nigh.<note place="margin">i. Peter. v.</note> Bee ſober and watche, for your oduerſary the
<pb facs="tcp:20475:35"/>
deuill as a roaring Lyon, walketh about, ſéekyng whom he maye deuoure: whom reſiſte, ſtedfaſt in the faith. Who is this, ſaieth Peter, that prouoketh you to this wicked inuention, that ye demaunde ſo wittely what we ſhall doe, if theſe vaine paſtymes were laide a parte? he ſaieth plainely that it is the Deuil, who goeth roryng about ſeekyng whom he maie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure, where doeth he ſearche to deuour you? in your faieth ſaith the Apoſtle, for if ye applie youre ſelues to the deedes of faith, without the whiche (ſaieth Paule) it is impoſſible to pleaſe God.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ebrewes. xi.</note> As to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reneſſe of liuing,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uke. i.</note> to the forſaking of the deuill with all his woorkes,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Peter. i.</note> to followe the deedes of the ſpirite.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ala. v.</note> Then foorth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with rageth the aduerſarie, then fumeth the deuill, then ſeeketh he whom he maie deuour. But followe the appetite of the wicked fleſhe, and ſaciate her luſt and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, and ye ſhall be his faire children, ye ſhalbe chekens méete for his owne tooth, he ſhall ſtrike your heades, and make ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry muche of you, for ye are well worthie, ſeyng ye are ſeruantes meete for ſuch a
<pb facs="tcp:20475:35"/>
maiſter.<note place="margin">Pſalme. xviii.</note> Dice, carde, tennes, boule, play and cheſſe, with al other fleſhly paſtimes, day &amp; night. Laie on othes, teare god with al his holy members as ſmall as hearbes to the pot. And the deuil wil neuer hinder you, neuer roare at you, hee will neuer ſéeke who he may deuour: for he hath you faſt knit to the deedes of darkenes.<note place="margin">Rom. xiii.</note> And kéepeth you ſtil in the ſame, as children of vnbeléefe.<note place="margin">Ephe. ii.</note> And what needeth the deuill to ſeeke for them, ſeyng thei ſeeke ſo faſt to runne to hym, with the paſſyng awaie of time, in ſuch vaine ſportes and recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the wit, and ſolacing of the mind? Therefore after the counſell of Peter, be ſober and watche yet a very little while, and he that ſhall come, will come and wil not tarie.<note place="margin">Hebrewes x</note> He will not tarie (ſaith Paul) againe or twoo at the Tables, Cardes, Cheſſe or Dice, and then haue with ye, ſaie you, paſſe awaie the tyme at youre pleaſure, apply your ſelues to ſuche vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as long as ye liſte, demaunde what ye ſhould doe, how ye ſhoulde ſpende the tyme, if theſe wicked gamenynges were laide aſide, as often as ye liſt? Paule ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb facs="tcp:20475:36"/>
you a plaine aunſwere, that he that commeth, will come, and will not tarie. For if with all expedition and readines, he would haue his diſciple followe hym, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he intended a matter of no leſſe god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, then neceſſarie: as to burie his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atth. viii.</note> He graunted hym no libertie, but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded hym, to followe him ſtraight waie, and to ſuffer the dead to burie their deade. And thinke you that he will tarie your leaſure, tyll ye haue plaide a game or two, in a matter of wickednes that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faceth Gods glory (for as muche as it is a deede of the fleſhe (and preiudiciall to the edification of your neighbour? no, no. He that commeth: will come and will not tarie. Therfore if thou wilt knowe, how thou ſhouldeſt be occupied, if theſe vaine paſtymes were laied a ſide, reſort nowe and then, yea, rather continually,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>c. i.</note> to the moſte holſome worde of God, and there meditate and exerciſe thy ſelfe, and if thou canſte not reade, then lette thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes or Children reade vnto thee, if none of theim can reade, then feare the vengeaunce of GOD, for thy negligente
<pb facs="tcp:20475:36"/>
bryngyng vp of theim. For the good free ſhall bee knowen by his fruicte, and the had tree like wiſe.<note place="margin">Math. vii.</note> And Paule compteth hym that prouideth not for his owne and ſpecially for theim of his houſholde: to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the faithe, and to bée worſe then an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidell.<note place="margin">i. Timo. v.</note> And to the Galathians<note place="margin">Galat. v.</note> he calleth the houſholde of faithe, that in Timothe he called his owne houſholde. Let there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your youthe bee godlie inſtructe. For as the common biworde is, ſuche a father ſuche a ſonne, ſuche a maiſter, ſuche a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt: and as the heade of the houſholde is, ſo are the members<note place="margin">Pſalme. xvii</note> And Dauid alſo, calleth the familie bleſſed, that feare the Lorde.<note place="margin">Pſalme. cxx<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> For in the verteous nourte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng of the children, conſiſteth the quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of all Realmes, and namely in ſuche as are made vnto the ſimilitude of their Lorde GOD.<note place="margin">Geneſis. i.</note> Therefore in ſeaſon, let theim taſte of the ſweete woorde of God, and ſauour of the kyngdome of heauen,<note place="margin">Pſalm. xxxi</note> that thei in the ſame holie woorde, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte bothe you and theim ſelues. And as I ſaied vnto you, if ye liſte to knowe how to paſſe awaie the tyme: buſie your myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des
<pb facs="tcp:20475:37"/>
in the Sacred Bible, and taſte howe pleaſaunte the Lorde is.<note place="margin">Peter. i.</note> And when ye haue ſaciate your myndes therein, fall to praier and ſupplication, and deſire thy al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie Father, who fulfilled the whole ſomme of his woorde, in his ſonne Chriſt.<note place="margin">Timo. i.</note> That for his reuerence and worthines, he will illuminate the eyes of thy fleſhly harte, that thou maieſt obtaine the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte ſence of the ſame.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lm. cxviii.</note> Then marke what vocation thou art of. If thou art the chief ruler of the people, and the principal emong the members, and the heade of the congregation. I exhort thee, for conſcience ſake, lette neuer this queſtion enter into youre ſtomacke, to demaunde what ſhall wee doe to paſſe awaie the tyme in trifles of follie? But rather ponder theſe three thynges, what knowledge is there in our Realme, if that bée wantyng, fall to drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng with Salomon that wiſe ruler, and God ſhall appeare, and giue you your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſte, therefore inquire for knowledge, and ye ſhall haue it aboundantly, and the thynges alſo that ye require not, ſhall bee giuen vnto you.<note place="margin">Regum. 3.</note> Wherefore looke dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently,
<pb facs="tcp:20475:37"/>
what knowledge raigneth in your Realme: Then marke what feare of God there is in you, to delate the true woorde of GOD, and what an harte you haue to maintaine the ſame. For the feare of God is the beginnyng of wiſedome.<note place="margin">Prouer. i.</note> And ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore, ye that be the gouernours of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, feare GOD, and ye ſhall ratefie the thynges that be good.<note place="margin">Eccleſi. xv.</note> Thirdly, mittigate youre hartes, and ſubdue your myndes, hauyng no reſpecte vnto the ſublimitie, and ſuperioritie of your ſtate, in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to your ſubiectes, but rather in ſubiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to your Lorde God. And marke well that you are miniſters, yea, miniſters I ſaie to hym, vnto whom you ſhall make a ſtraight accompte.<note place="margin">Hebre. xiii.</note> And here remember, that in as muche as ye are the miniſters of God, God hath giuen you a ſworde in your hande, to deface malefactours, and to preſerue the innocent. Therefore, occupie it to Goddes glorie.<note place="margin">Roma. xiii.</note> And to the ſubuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the bloudie kingdome of Antichriſt: after the example of kyng Ihon.<note place="margin">iiii. Regum</note> And all wee your true louyng ſubiectes, will har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely maintaine you, with our praiers to
<pb facs="tcp:20475:38"/>
GOD, who alwaies preſerue you.<note place="margin">Timo. ii.</note> And here reſte and quiete youre ſelues, to the glorie of God: for in theſe three thynges, are many thynges to bewailed. If thou be a Spirituall iudge of Chriſtes flocke, or a ſuperintendent of his congregation. Is it meete to demaunde, how thou ſhalt paſſe awaie the tyme, if ſuche vaine paſtymes are laied a ſide? No, no, there ſhould be no ſuche vndiſcrete woordes or language, and ſpecially emong ſuche perſones. For, youre communication, is a ſore incitation to the common ſorte of the people: For of your woordes dooe thei wholie depende. The more pitie, if it pleaſed God: without thei were as the wordes of God.<note place="margin">Peter. iiii.</note> You re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce very muche, to haue taken your po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and aucthoritie of Peter, and learne ye theſe leſſons of hym, then am I decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued? For I am ſure, he made no ſuche an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere vnto Chriſte, when he demaunded of him,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on. xxi.</note> whether he did loue hym or no. He aunſwered hym, yea lorde, thou knoweſt that I loue thée. If ye compte Peter to be your predeceſſour, then folowe the inſam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of hym, and loue Chriſte. What muſt
<pb facs="tcp:20475:38"/>
ye dooe then, if ye loue? Muſte ye applie youre ſelues to Dicyng, Cardyng, Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng, and Haukyng? No, that is not the waie to folowe Peter. What then? Fede my ſheepe, ſaieth Chriſte to Peter. Now then, if ye loue Chriſte with Peter, ye muſt with Peter feede, feede, not Palfre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yes, Geldynges, Horſes, and a kenell of Dogges, but my ſheepe, ſaieth Chriſt. In deede Chriſte, often tymes by a certaine metapher, and phraiſe of ſpeakyng, doeth mutuate and borowe, the vnreaſonable, for the reaſonable, as it appeareth in the xxj. and alſo in the tenth of ſaincte Ihon,<note place="margin">Ihon. x. &amp;. x<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> where he ſaieth, a good Shepherde will giue his life for his Sheepe. Yet all the worlde in a maner will teſtifie, that he died neither for Sheepe, nor Oxen.<note place="margin">i. Corin. ix.</note> But for the Chriſtian Congregation he died.<note place="margin">Eſaic. liii.</note> So when he commaunded Peter, and you in Peter (if ye be his true ſucceſſors) with <hi>paſce, paſce,</hi> fede, fede, that ye ſhould feede that Congregation, the whiche he died for, that his beloued ſpouſe, the holie Catholike Churche, of the whiche he is the heade.<note place="margin">Ephe. vi.</note> But I praie GOD, ye feede
<pb facs="tcp:20475:39"/>
them not, as the Prophet Ezechiel in his xxxiiij.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. xxxiiii.</note> Chapiter ſpecifieth, ſaiyng. Wo bee vnto the Shepheardes of Iſrael, that feede them ſelues: ſhould not the Shepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heardes feede their flockes? Ye haue ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vp the fatte, ye haue clothed your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues with the wolle. The beſte fedde haue ye ſlaine, but the flocke haue ye not nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed. The weake haue ye not holden vp The ſicke haue ye not healed, the broken haue ye not bounde together. The outca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes haue ye not brought againe. The loſt haue ye not ſoughte, but churliſhely, and moſte cruelly haue ye ruled them. Theſe thinges are right contrary, and cleane be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the commaundement, that Peter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued of our ſauiour Chriſt. For he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded hym to feede the flocke, and not to eate awaie the fat from their beardes, and feede theim ſelues, and (in the meane while) lette the flocke ſtarue for lacke of foode. This is not to feede of loue, but of compulſion.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ter. v.</note> Not for Chriſtes ſake, but for the beallies ſake.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i. iii.</note> Marke nowe Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chielles Prophecie with a ſingle eye: and fulfill the thynges that he, with the reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due
<pb facs="tcp:20475:39"/>
of the Prophets appoincteth you, and ye ſhall finde more neceſſary thinges per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainyng to your office, then to caſte holie water, and deale holie breade, or to bidde faſtyng, or holie daies on the So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>daie. For if you looke well on your duetie, and ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacke euery corner thereof, none other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, then ye ſhall at the comptyng daie, giue an aunſwere therefore.<note place="margin">Ezech. iii.</note> Ye ſhall (if ye haue any conſcience, or any dreade of god before your eyes) haue ſmall affection to demaunde, how ye ſhal paſſe awaie the tyme, if theſe vanities were laied aſide. But in no wiſe howe ſoeuer ye doe, what ſo euer is written, or ſpoken vnto you, take little héede to your ſelues. But yet I ſaie, beware againſte the tyme, and haue youre aunſwere in a readineſſe, when it ſhall bee ſaied vnto you, giue accompte of thy Bailiwike: for thou maieſt no longer bee Bailife.<note place="margin">Luke. xvi,</note> Therefore bée not offended, although I write the truth, for ye knowe where the woordes bee conteined: not in my imagination, but in the ſacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. If ye bee offended therewith, reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that God and his woorde are all one
<pb facs="tcp:20475:40"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n. i.</note> Nowe conclude the ſequele your ſelues, for ye know my minde. If thou be a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, or ſeculare iudge, remember well that then there is no tyme reſerued, for thee to demaunde, howe ye ſhall paſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie the tyme in ſuche trifles of folie: but rather daie and night, ponder and weighe what is lawful and right.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>che. ii.</note> In your iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente bee equall and righteous: and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently ſearche out the truthe.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eremi. v.</note> If ye haue executed the law vnrightouſly (the which of it ſelfe, is verie iuſte and true) learne now to doe right, applie your ſelues to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, deliuer the oppreſſed, helpe the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſſe to his right: lette the widdowes complainte come before you.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e, i.</note> Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that ye oughte to bee learned, ye that exerciſe the lawes vpon the yearth, leaſt ye periſhe from the right waie.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>m. ii.</note> So that by ſuche knowledge, ye maie diſcerne, neither to fauour the poore, neither to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure the mightie,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ter. v.</note> but to pronounce the iudgement of the lorde,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i. iii.</note> and to iudge your neighbours in righteouſneſſe.<note place="margin">iticus. xix.</note> Nowe, weigh theſe thynges a right, and exerciſe theim accordyng vnto youre office, as ye
<pb facs="tcp:20475:40"/>
ſhall giue accompte for it, at the laſte daie when ye your ſelues ſhall bee iudged, as ye haue iudged other.<note place="margin">Luke. vi.</note> And ioyne a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian mannes life thereto, that is, to ſerue GOD in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe, al the daies of your life.<note place="margin">Luke. i.</note> And then marke in what corner of a pure conſcience, thou ſhalte demaunde how thou ſhalte occupie the daies and nightes, to paſſe awaie the tyme. If thou bée of the inferiour ſort, and of the vulgare companie, thou haſte thy duetie ſhewed thee before: Sauyng this one thyng remaineth, that ye muſte con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, in as muche as ye are ſubiectes, ye muſt liue in all ſubmiſſion, and lowlines, and in true obedience toward your rulers &amp; gouernours, as Paul plainely recordeth to the Romaines.<note place="margin">Roma. xiii</note> Let euery ſoule ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte hym ſelf vnto the aucthorite of the higher powers. Here GOD excepteth no manne, no not hym, that weareth three Crownes at once, nor none of his rable, be he ſpiritual or temporall, if he be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended vnder the name of a ſubiect (as all men be, ſauyng the Rulers only) For that Paule here calleth euerie liuyng
<pb facs="tcp:20475:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſoule: me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are expert in the Hebrewe tongue dooe call it euery liuyng man. Now of the triple crowned gentleman, that Antechriſt of Rome be a liuing man (as I thinke he is, without there bee an alteration made in nature, as there hath before this time béen in his predeceſſour) he muſte by the rule of Paule, put of his crownes, and laye them at the temporall rulers feete. And fall to repentance, that by his vſurped power he hath ſuffered ſo many of his ſuperiours to kneele and to kiſſe his filthie feete. And therfore in this behalfe, I compte hym, as I doe all other of his order beſide, verie ſubiectes, euen equall with them, that are of the loweſt ſorte, of the temporalitie: yea equal with them that ought to waſhe mens feete.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. xiii.</note>
And therefore as manye as bee ſubiectes, muſte liue in all lowlines and iuſt obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence vnto their rulers and gouernours, yea, although they be infidels.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. xiii.</note> And to this doeth Peter well agree, ſaiyng, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit your ſelues vnto all maner of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of man for the lordes ſake. &amp;c. So long as they ordeine nothyng contrarie
<pb facs="tcp:20475:41"/>
to the expreſſe woorde of God.<note place="margin">Daniel. iii.</note> If they dooe: yet reſiſt them not with power of viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, but with the word and pacience,<note place="margin">Ierem. xxx<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> but be thou ſtedfaſte in the promiſe,<note place="margin">Math. v.</note> and ſuffer for conſcience ſake. For he that reſiſteth, ſhall receiue to hym ſelfe damp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: for as much as he reſiſteth the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaunce of God.<note place="margin">Roma. xiii.</note> I would therfore that our ſpirituall father ſhould take heede in tyme, and put his Sworde into the Sca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barde againe.<note place="margin">Math. xxvi.</note> For without the greate mercie of God, they are all damned with the deuill of hell. Now therfore I exhort you by the mercifulnes of GOD, and by that affection that ye haue to bee buried with Chriſte in baptiſme.<note place="margin">Roma. vi.</note> And in that ye deſire to be holy as he is holy, in al ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of conuerſation,<note place="margin">s. Peter. i.</note> auoyde the wicked deedes of the fleſhe.<note place="margin">Gala. v.</note> And if ye be riſen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine with Chriſte, ſeeke thoſe thinges which are aboue, where he ſitteth on the right hande of God. Set your affections on heauenly thynges, and not on earthly thynges.<note place="margin">Colloſſ. iii.</note> And backebite not this poore and ſimple inuectiue, againſt theſe ſwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of vices if ye do, marke where ye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehende
<pb facs="tcp:20475:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>
it, and conferre the Scriptures withall, (for in a maner without Gods word is nothing ſpoken. Then if the ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture be true (as I truſte ye will graunt no leſſe) beware ye reſiſte not the trueth againſt your conſcience: but rather forte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie it to youre power and ſtrength, to the glory of God, and to the ſubuerſion of vices. And thus I commit you to the worde of his grace. God ſaue the Queene and her moſt hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Counſell, with the whole Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:20475:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶Theſe bookes are to bée ſolde at the ſigne of the blacke Boye at the little Northe doore of Poules.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustrations">
            <pb facs="tcp:20475:43"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>H K</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
